Zachary Stein huh dr. Zachary sign I
should say I wanted to talk to you you
know for a few reasons
the first thing you know that caught my
attention was was your interest in
Yvonne Ilic
or the fact that you think in and write
about Yvonne Ilic a little bit and that
seems to be an influence in your work
and in the 90s I read LH and it kind of
it kind of changed my world or it
changed how I saw the world like
radically in in some sense right and so
so I've been waiting for somebody to
come along and talk about the fact that
you know talk about D schooling society
and and and like you you're you
distinguish between education and
schooling right and you talk about a
kind of infinite what did you say an
infinite horizon of Education or
something like that and and and then and
then this limitation of schooling that
we have and the fact that we're in
between worlds in some sense you know
where whereas we we don't know you know
one mode of living and being seems to be
disintegrating including our education
system and and another one seems to be
trying to be born with all of this
existential threat so yeah so that's
kind of my introduction and why you know
there's a couple other reasons actually
why I'm interested in talking to you
because one other reason was maybe we
can talk about that later is that you
you said that you were a a dyslexic
successful dyslexic I think I think high
achieving
excuse me a high achieving a dyslexic
Ana and I think I think I'm not a high
achieving dyslexic but I think I'm a
dyslexic well you're a musician I'm also
a musician and that was the last thing
that was the last of the three things
that I was thinking of which made me
want to to talk to you
now besides you know listening to you
and and noticing that you had a very
clear and lucid voice and important
things to say so so can you talk about
this can you talk about Yvonne Ilitch
and sure eat schooling Society yeah I
mean it's it's one of the main threads
throughout my
book which you mentioned the education a
time between worlds is the title and
basically Ilic blew it away
you blew it away like and you read him
now and you're like how can it still be
the way it is given that Ivan Illich
wrote this you know that one namely D
schooling society and medical nemesis
yeah he gets into the multi-level
iatrogenic crises that plague modern
industrial societies but D school and
society is a remarkable book and even
more remarkable because it was written
before the internet like many of the
ideas that are within and are well I
would like to say that he's a prophet of
some kind like I put I put him in the
category of prophet not just thinker
yeah um you know totally well I mean he
was Catholic priest son so that sense of
the prophetic and then the actual
project voice that he had a prophetic
voice when hear him speak he has the
word sound power as the Rastas say you
know but there's also a way in which
because he had a religiosity
mm-hm it allowed his social critique to
be even deeper that he was actually
looking at evil and not as a secularist
explaining it away with evolutionary
theory because we evolved to be meat
machines that compete and kill but Ilic
no thinking that man has an eternal soul
and is yet doing this to himself sick
him namely and so Ilic was seeing very
clearly and was pulling no punches and
so yeah he saw what many people have
seen with the nature of large modern
school systems which is that they are at
their worst profoundly dehumanizing and
the apparatus of state control social
control
and ideological indoctrination there's a
bunch of things you can do with the
school system that you couldn't that you
couldn't do if you had a decentralized
community-based system of Education
where the parents basically took control
of their kids which is what it had been
for a very long time and you know what
we know of as schools are political
entities which began with the birth of
the capitalist world system you know
belong 16th century now education
predates that and other things which
we'd like to call school to predate that
but what we know with the desks and the
teachers and the routine and schedule
disciplines and the preparation for
entry into wage labor there's some one
thing you said you said education
predates that what do you mean by
education then I mean when you shouldn't
begin doesn't education begin with the
you know the first human in a way I mean
correct I mean you could argue that
education as I'm trying to define it is
a kind of species specific trait that
and this is like Michael Tomasello
there's at the Max Planck Institute for
a while really doing very careful
research differentiating primate
behavior from human behavior especially
abusive the intergenerational
transmission and score so of course
controversial because when you say well
animals don't educate one another
instantly you get the reaction yes of
course they do and of course they do but
what happens is very very different when
a monkey shows another monkey how to do
something then when adult human
enculturate s-- a infant into
toddlerhood into early childhood i mean
there's a qualitatively different kind
of intergenerational transmission which
may or may not involve schooling but
definitely involves a ton of intimate
exercise of what I call teach really
Authority yeah I like that word
transmission and and I think maybe
that's what's missing from the education
system is trend is a kind of
transmission no I actually think I mean
you're you're correct that it it's built
to not do
certain things but one of the reasons it
succeeds is because of the transmission
of individual teachers like despite the
system despite the fact that it's set up
to basically dehumanize the kids and to
make them into numbers and to turn them
into aged laborers the last kind of
thing that's left is actually the last
thing that's left is the choosing on the
front line sure doing the right thing in
the classroom actually loving the kids
and that was my experience where I felt
completely alienated in high school as
it dyslexic and so I took to music but I
had several teachers who just loved me
anyway and encouraged me anyway I'm
sorry it's - I don't have I'm too many
digressions here but but I'm interested
in how you did succeed as dyslexic like
I mean it was music that actually helped
you to succeed or something because I
wonder if our obstacles are sparse but
sometimes the thing that kind of pushes
us to excel a little bit further
sometimes even if it makes certain make
certain things kind of a struggle or
yeah well I mean there's two ways I
think about it one is that dyslexia it's
actually just a difference it's not a
disability just so actually there's only
a disability in a culture that involves
reading and specifically in alphabetic
reading culture and a pictographic
reading culture you don't have things
like this Fox Theater know you have
different things the ideas that you have
a like a difference neurologically that
interfaces with the culture in a
particular way and in our culture with
our alphabet and the English language in
particular in the way it's taught you
know this luckily just means bad at
reading that's literally what the word
means bad like there's only recently
that we're trying to tease apart the why
are you bad at reading and it turns out
there's many forms of dyslexia yeah and
some of them you've got a lot of books
behind you and you read a lot obviously
I read a ton which means I'm obviously
not the kind of dislikes like that
struggles with with reading so the
nature of your dyslexia is something
different then well I mean so there's so
I haven't looked at the literature in a
while when I was in graduate school I
looked at it closely and there were two
kinds of dyslexia the most
Gordon and well-liked that's not true
the the kind that we thought was the
only kind for a long time had to do
actually with phoneme and grapheme
recognition right so can the Year parse
the speech stream right and can you
relate the parsed speech stream to the
grapheme appearing on the say and so is
actually some forms of deafness and
other forms of basically auditory
difference that ended up making it so
that they couldn't figure out the parts
of speech on like auditorally and then
it confused what they were doing with
their eyes then there's another form of
dyslexia which I believe I have which
just has to do with the ratio of foveal
to peripheral vision right that's
something like eighty percent of the
people in the population have better
foveal vision than peripheral vision
which is to say like they see better
narrowly right in front of them than
they do like out if you hold your arms
out and wave your fingertips at the
edges of your vision like you're
peripherally huh but there's some
percentage of the population which
actually have really good peripheral
vision and they're phobia vision was
kind of not great they're actually
mostly getting the gestalt and not
getting the detail oh that's me holy cow
that's exactly so that's what I am dude
you can see obviously in some contexts
better peripheral vision would be that
would be selected for so that's why it
would still be in the system it's only
recently that we would be selecting
against this and that's one of my
arguments and when I came up and into
this critique of standardized testing
because it may be that dyslexics
actually should be selected for and we
should build a system that doesn't
select against people who actually
perceives a gestalt rather than the
details and so when I read I actually
have struggled with spelling because I
don't read at the level of the grapheme
or the word necessarily I read something
like at the level of the sentence for
the paragraph blows me away because it
sounds so familiar to my experience and
I guess my next question is how what
does that have to do with your interest
or even my interest in in music how does
that relate to music
that's a good question I mean you know
it's about one way to think about what's
happening here is you know it's about
the perception of patterns and the
perception of structure and different
ways of doing that and so you know I was
drawn to improvisational music in
particular and music that involved very
little orchestration essentially like
Indian classical music like Miles Davis
from the electric period like a bitches
brew and these things we've got long 20
minute tracks with just a couple of
chords set and then a ton of free form
improvisation and my experience in that
was precisely the ability to not be
involved in detail at a certain level
and to feel the whole to feel the whole
thing as opposed to planning and out in
the minutiae and so I gravitated to
music perhaps because I gravitated to
that kind of experience
so you didn't gravitate to the Western
classical tradition I imagine if you're
like me it's the same thing III I could
relate to Indian sounds I could relate
to African sounds I could relate to you
know I could write kids it's a
psychedelic music I could relate to you
know jazz and and all that but I
couldn't I couldn't get into you know
Mozart or Beethoven or I can only I can
I only like soloists like I could get
into Glenn Gould or something like that
but I is that similar to you or are we
yeah we're similar I mean I played
trumpet you know I've actually played
trumpet grade school and but reading
music was always hard again because of
my peripheral vision so I actually kind
of played by ear I'm an illiterate
musician also yeah my grandfather wasn't
a literate musician and he played jazz
like you wouldn't believe it he could
just jump on a piano and do Oscar
Peterson exactly you know so so but he
was he was an illiterate musician and
you know
but in and of course Ornette Coleman and
I mean do this along yes there you go
Jimi Hendrix I mean there's a long list
of musicians who couldn't read music and
then so this is the educational question
so who do you select for driver who gets
promoted and awarded with official
musicianship status the ones who have to
read this particular kind of music or
the ones who can play almost any time
type of music by just receiving Stolte
of the whole but the whole group is
doing so yeah but of course I came to
appreciate Bach like maybe a decade ago
and so I do you know appreciate Western
music but there's also this you know
taking it into the well-tempered scale
right and moving out of the what's
called the just intonation or the kind
of given physics of Pythagorean reality
and moving it into something that can be
moved across multiple pianos and
actually the key they know the keys
stacking so that's another difference to
I was always drawn to Indian classical
music and and the Blues and things that
were actually interesting yeah yeah
attempting to to kind of like question
the you know kind of the the overbearing
nature of the of the Western structure
of music itself that's the whole blues
note when you pull the blues note down
on the guitar so it's like in-between
what notes yeah exactly
well I was a played I play fretless
featherless bass and so I actually in
college before I did anything seriously
with books I I was being trained in
Indian classical music on the bass you
know like John McLaughlin like Shakti
style and that was amazing I know so
much had to do with playing between and
playing between the notes that
officially exist right yeah no one I'm
playing actually doesn't officially
exist I can't actually put it on paper
and that was gratifying to me because
on paper didn't seem as real as reality
and also and also you don't want to just
imitate things you want to kind of take
things a step further or step out into
chaos a little bit and come back to
order or something like that yeah yeah
beautiful thing about about that kind of
music or yeah whereas you know I
remember I in Morocco I met a guy he
said that you know Moroccan music it
just goes on and on like you can't fit
it on a CD it's it's a long story and
also when he hears western music it
sounds like it hasn't holes in it it's
like yeah it's missing something's
missing this in-between for him that
that was his perception right was you
know we would hear kind of a noise or
yes I perceived the dyslexia as as an
advantage actually like overall that the
nervous system is different not
necessarily disabled in certain contexts
it was a huge disadvantage and you know
I succeeded kind of by luck you know and
the grace of good teachers I think and
then certain kind of passion that I had
which I don't I can't kind of like take
responsibility for just there and has to
do with the course that my life took but
yeah so I did eventually read a lot of
books even though I was dyslexic and do
a lot of writing but writing of course
if we were to look over my shoulder when
I write you think what the hell is wrong
with this guy's eye candy smells as he
spells like an eighth grader like I can
barely function with the keyboard you
know it takes a very long time to
construct the instrument well I write
really quickly and then I write I write
and then I rewrite narrator I write
super quickly and I make tons of
mistakes and then I go back and I fix
all the mistakes that's the only way I
can do it I can't I don't understand
people who are so fluid and could just
write no it's for me it's like you know
kind of almost sculpting like at least
if I'm trying to really articulate
something clearly other times if I've
written you know I wrote a book of
poetry I would just I would just kind of
I would let the the the error or the
mistake you know
remain on the page I think there's other
forms of writing where or you can do
that right mmm
yeah so what about what about what about
meditation and I know that you you've
worked with Ken Wilber for a long time
and and I wonder about spiritual
practice if that informs you know how
you view all of this it does definitely
yeah I can was a huge influence on me
his books and then I began to work with
him myself
mark Gaffney him mark Gaffney - right
yeah may the Center for integral wisdom
and you know during that period yes I
practiced and very I'm actually the very
kind of a very serious meditate and I'd
also studied Kabbalah and Christian
traditions of contemplator prayer so
that that weaves in and it and I think
it has - it's part of the themes of the
book about the between world nuts the
between world neces in a sense between
definitions of sacredness or between
forms of religiosity forms of meaning
making and even forms of legitimacy and
so there's a there's a need to return to
those both traditions and you know the
the practices they imply that my
transcend any given tradition so examine
for example yeah I hate to say this
because it sounds so ridiculous but I
also started in Zen so I'm we have so
many things in common it seems you know
I also did a lot of Zen practice when
I'm in my 20s right while I was reading
Ivan Illich and Ken Wilber books and
people forget the early ones like the
oblong project for example everyone
thinks of the four quadrants and this
things which came much much later he he
was first and foremost a you know
transpersonal psychologist kind of the
transpersonal psychologist and said he
was you know the admin project was
written for meditators and
psychotherapists and people who were
mostly concerned
about the psyche and its transformation
and salvation and that in that sense
yeah ken was a gift in the sense to me
when I when I and and then of course
moving into Harvard and going to
graduate school ended up subsuming him
and a ton of other yeah in a ton of
other stuff but as I say in the book it
he'd left a deposit in my honking that I
think it's something also I can't take
credit for you said he had laudable
faults I like that phrase it's a lot of
liabilities it was and you said at the
end of your book was right the end of
your book that you know our strengths
are close to our weaknesses and yeah and
I was thinking like I was thinking one
of the things that's kind of disgusting
about our culture at the moment is you
take a guy like Ken Wilber and you have
to have this opinion about him like
before or against and in some kind of
strong dichotomous you can't just like
you know take what is incredibly
valuable there and you know not
subscribe to everything and you know
because we all have faults right yeah
now you're touching on the crisis of tea
truly authority right that our culture
actually doesn't know how to deal with
teach really Authority and that means it
doesn't know how to be a student because
we've consumed we've confused the role
of student as learning with the role of
student as consumer so for against it's
like voting or shopping whereas learning
is much much more complex and teach
really a teacher the authority is much
more nuanced than just you take
everything or leave everything and
teachers know that yeah good teachers
anyway and so yeah you're right it's a
very difficult situation to be in as a
culture when it's impossible to
establish the necessary dynamics of
teach really Authority that could
facilitate intergenerational
transmission to perpetuate civilization
so you end up getting a catastrophic
bifurcation of intergenerational
transmission which looks like you don't
have anything to teach me
yeah and but on the other side I don't
have anything to offer that's right and
I was also thinking I'm also a teacher
and I was thinking with my students that
that I was as asked him one time do you
have any heroes yeah is there anybody
that came up to or aspire to be like and
it's like no like it's like it seems
like in the society having somebody
higher than you as an offense like we're
all supposed to be exactly the same or
you know Authority would beam that you
would you know you would love somebody
and and what you know even want to be
them in a sense or not to be like them
but well you see if you were to expand
it beyond reality you would get them to
admire certain characters and stories
and TV shows and things of that nature
and so it actually has to do with a
displacement into the simulation and
into fantasy that's part of the kind of
late lean capitalist cultural industry
so yeah that there's a confusion about
yeah how to how to receive how to grow
on with the help of others help they get
it in the simulacrum is what you mean
like yeah like on Netflix or right
through watching you know endless dramas
or right is that that's one way to view
it and then the you know I think the you
know the difficulties compounded by the
actual errors and mistakes of supposed
thority right so it's like if it's if we
could find a way for everyone to lose
face together as opposed to needing one
party to lose face and the other party
triumphs so the difficulty with the
teach early Authority is that you know
of course teachers are incomplete right
like of course we needed to find a way
for Western culture for example to tell
certain histories right about certain
people's and actions and we need to be
able to grapple with that as a culture
and then see tragedy and move into
something like a post tragic form of
cultural authority yeah before that
we're stuck
in the situation where everyone's
calling on everyone else to lose face
and to relinquish authority but by whose
authority in your book as well that that
idea of post post tragedy it's like the
tragedy is like the postmodern era right
where everything just gets reduced and
then the post tragedy is is is sort of
now that everything's broken you're just
trying to find the pieces and put them
back together and well yeah I mean and
you know the the postmodern is that is
the kind of surfacing of the tragic
that's one way one way to view it and
now you can't get stuck in tragedy you
know you can't get stuck in just shadow
work and doing endless circles and
bringing up all the dark stuff like
that's not the goal you know like you
can't get stuck in retelling the horrors
of colonialism and you can't get stuck
in like there's we need to tell these
and so it's not either/or
we can't not tell them because then the
kids get to say we're illegitimate
teacher the authorities and we would be
right so we can't lie and we can't avoid
the truth but we need to grapple with
the tragic
we can't displace it we can't get stuck
in it either and so that's the
postmodern malaise or fragmentation or
inertia is that there's nothing beyond
the tragic and that's the zombie myth I
was talking to John drove a key about
this zombie is the anti tragic figure
because there's no redemption for him
he's just as he just remains a zombie
there's no end to the there's no there's
no end to the zombie stories they just
keep multiplying whereas whereas in a
tragic in a tread in a real tragedy
there's there's a kind of catharsis you
get you get from from as you say
grappling with right Brent Brandon yeah
no I mean the
yeah and it's not that the post tragic
is the resolution of the tragedy or
somehow when the music kicks back in and
everyone's smiling and the story wraps
up right it's not the post tragic the
post tragic actually
continues to reside in the tragic and so
case what do you mean by that that's
very interesting yeah the post tragic
continues to reside within the tragic in
other words you're saying that you're
saying we can't deny the tragic I'm
saying you absolutely can't deny tragedy
and in fact you can't avoid it and yet
your looks square at it I mean death for
example yeah okay this is Illinois about
that the medical system actually steals
from us the art of dealing with our own
suffer and it steals from us the dignity
of confronting pain and death on our own
terms and so that's an example of
looking at tragedy as opposed to
actually putting tragedy off onto
someone else as their responsibility
whereas death is something that we can
look at every day and in a sense your
deaths a tragedy but in another sense
once you've looked at it long enough you
realize it's the reason that you're
living and so similarly with other
tragedies if you stay in it long enough
yeah it transforms and so this is what
we're being called to do into that sort
of sweetness of impermanence or
I mean in it and it steals into a new
form of character or identity you know
that the tragedy is you in a certain
place in time and that the you on the
other side of the tragedy is different
you know the alchemists talk about kind
of darkening or pewter occasion they're
blackening right and that there's the
dissolution and the calling up and the
remembrances of
the you know another how commence rains
would be something like the unendurable
image right the unendurable images into
the tragedy this is the thing that you
can't stand to imagine the thought that
you can't hold but these are the exactly
the thought you need to hold until it
changes and until the darkening and the
purification allows for the emergence of
something new that wouldn't have been
there without it and so you know the
tragic things often the thing that
cannot be resolved and just fixed it's
the thing that needs to be served and so
yeah again this is the issue but if we
can't get out of crises of teacher the
authority and denial so the post truth
thing goes both ways right the post
truth in both denies the tragedies
happened and on the other side denies
that there's a way out of tragedy right
and which is to say there needs to be
true fir there'd be a way out of tragedy
right and there needs to be legitimacy
authentic Authority you know things like
morality and ethics that matter these
narrative you know because
post-modernism is the death of all
narratives but right so so you kind of
refined the golden thread of the
narrative right if the golden thread the
narrative and the and the ability again
to for everyone to lose face together
like what is that language even look
like do we have that language you know
it's not everyone's all folk together
that's not the solution it's can
everyone lose face together like what is
that language even look like for that
and who right now when I said that's
like well I mean how my group well the
word that came to mind when you said
that was a tone meant or something yeah
atonements a good word
[Music]
so I don't know how exactly we got to
this point but well the next really deep
yeah we're in pretty deep actually I I
tend to skip formalities and things like
this in this podcast because maybe
because of some of the frustration you
spoke with the kind of form of a podcast
so anyway the next the next place that
this leads to is is is you have this
idea of concrete utopia so so we have
tragedy and then we have post tragedy
and now we have concrete utopia do you
want you want to get into that your 13
utopias or so they yeah the 13 social
miracles as a form of concrete utopian
fear mmm-hmm yeah I mean obviously the
word utopia we can trace it and that's a
pejorative at this point utopia right
exactly that's why I wanted you to know
and you know it's interesting because
I've been doing a lot of work studying
like the 30 Years War in Europe and the
secret societies within that that usher
goes through from the Renaissance to the
Enlightenment there was a dicey period
with the Inquisition's and the 30 Years
War which is kind of the first world war
and this figure IMO's John Amos Comenius
is the greatest educational reformer
we've ever lived and basically was
working right after bacon right that's
her right after the first utopians like
wrote their utopias and so he took the
utopian scheme which ended up being kind
of like infused with a certain rustic
Russia essence and then began to go
around Europe talking to all the kings
convincing them to make the utopia
concrete Comenius was actually one of
the first concrete utopian theorists in
history living in the 1600s basically
turning specifically More's utopia
solomon's temple within it the
educational reforms of like a full-stack
technological society it's fascinating
stuff and so the idea to conquer utopia
is that you find a way to
exercise the imagination like the social
imagination in a much much more radical
way based on something that looks like
utopian theorizing based on like
principles right based on ideals and
then you begin to try to relate it
directly to what's actually exist and so
it's kind of the only way to do critical
theory if you actually think about it
like a woman named Ben Habib I think
wrote a book called critique in utopia I
think it was comments that Hamas and all
the critical theorists basically saying
and you look at critical theory there's
always the utopian moment and the
diagnostic moment there's always the
moment of critique and there's always
the moment of laying out the vision of
what could be better now often the
vision of what could be better is
implicit
it's crypto you never say it you're just
critiquing dirty critiquing but implicit
in the critique is that there's some way
that it might not be that way right that
there's some way that's not bad so
there's always there's always the
utopian moment in any kind of step of
criticism so the concrete utopians
ended up doing that work where they're
actually suggesting it in almost an
insane way they're almost kind of like
saying hey wait have you stopped and
slowed down actually look at this we
could do it very very differently let's
use a couple of thought experiments that
seem utopian to begin to spark the
imagination to get us thinking about
what to actually do on the ground and so
Roy Bhaskar was where I got the actual
term from concrete utopian theorizing
because he was so you know kind of
disgruntled with the the crypto
normative ISM of post-modernism which is
the sign of critique the critique the
critique the critique always implying
that there is an actual better way but
never stating the better way because if
you state the better way then now you're
open to critique but if you just
critique critique critique and then have
a crypto normative ISM which you smuggle
in the utopian moment behind the scenes
that never talked about it
and so Bhaskar started to
basically a kind of like concrete
utopian thicker theorizing to contre
kind of counteract you overtly and
pessimistic and nihilist thing kind of
critiques of the postmodernist so I kind
of take that up with the 13 social
miracles and basically run a set of five
experiments which are concrete utopian
experiments which are in one sense naive
but in another sense close enough to
actual reality to be provocative and to
be in a sense not a political platform
but a disciplined way of thinking about
futures you have something to aim for
yeah in a simple sense you have
something to aim for and otherwise
you're just you're just gonna spin
around in nihilism correct but it's also
that you're making explicit like it's a
it's a it's a come to terms with what
you need to imagine actually get there
yeah right like if we need to step out
of the languages of critique and get
into the languages of commitment let's
say then we need to actually play a
different kind of language game where
we're no longer yelling at one another
about how we suck and actually
collaborating on what we might build
together that would be preferable yeah
and that's also traditional in a way too
because that's the promised land or the
city on the hill or you know correct
yeah we've always lived 11 yeah as a
framework of you know where we need to
go or something like that right yeah no
I mean that's you know there's a great
book I can't remember the guy but it's
called the image of the future and
basically it's this note he tracks it
all the way through the ancient sea like
we've always had these profound images
of what the human will become basically
and they used to be apocalyptic and very
dramatic and or they weren't but you
know we've lost that we in a sense weak
and I've said this somewhere like you
know CAPA
can't imagine its own infinitely which
is to say like there's there's a limit
to the imagination of what we can
conceive right now is possible socially
because of the habituation
to the current civilization and so
that's the other thing that concur
utopian theorizing the students
disrupting a virtual thought pattern or
at least attempting to and again it's
not novel you know I think a lot of
science fiction tries to do this usually
we get dystopian science fiction but
usually in the dystopian science fiction
there's like a couple images of a
utopian kind of setup and so yeah so
there's the possibility to begin to
restructure the social imagination by
doing concrete utopian theorizing on
scale and in popular culture as opposed
to having zombie movies having movies
that portray a near-future scenario
that's extremely realistic where things
start going well and you show what the
technology applications could actually
look like and how things could be
different with medicine and education
and show a world that's actually working
that's close enough to this world that
actually ends up being very critical of
this world like I think around 2000 you
know around the time Trump was elected
you could say I started even though like
this was a kind of traumatic moment for
for everybody on some level this was
also the moment and I'm not I'm not
saying Trump's a great guy I already
thing like that I think this was kind of
the moment I think of wherewhere where I
started to think that okay everything's
falling apart so then this is the moment
where a constructive new purposing could
could it could occur right and then I
started coming up with finding people
like Alexander Bardot was talking about
the Eco topia and you know that being a
constructive concept and talking about
just constructive concepts right and you
hadn't even hadn't even considered that
there would be constructive concepts
like it's just like cuz you know I it
would be just I would just be in my in
in the woods
doing tantric buddhic Buddhist practice
and that would be it but I but in in the
in the general culture I think I didn't
think anything was going on right and
now I have this slight feeling that like
something's going on and you're talking
about it and other people are talking
about it that there's actually something
going on right now and the comparison to
that to the thirty years war and that
shift in the world system with
convenient Kongregate opium vision and
that being held together with kind of a
bunch of constructive theorizing
happening behind the scenes this is
what's happening now we're transitioning
the whole civilizations transition thank
you right or its end or ten things right
and that's always a possibility you need
to keep in your mind as well right both
of those things you know well and
they're both they're both true like if
something new does emerge then this
civilization ends if something new
doesn't emerge this civilization also
ends now it's two different ways of
ending the civilization and yeah there
is a sense that when things start to
break apart that you get new
possibilities new light shining through
that it's precisely because we don't
have one hegemonic narrative anymore
they were getting on if people
triangulating true that's from different
angles that never would have been seen
because of the dominance of the one
narrative now the apps the complete
absence of narrative is starting to
become a problem
sure again we're between worlds and
being between worlds means that there is
an absence of go ahead coherent
narrative how could it be otherwise
given the scope of planet ization in the
past century right that this is a phase
specific developmentally appropriate
like transition of humanization planet
cessation as T liard Road is a weapon no
road as Geoffrey West writes as is
obvious but we're still out kill one
another go for soil and the color of our
skin so the question is not learning
learning takes care of itself the
question is why aren't we learning the
question is as however mas one said it's
not learning
it's not learning that's the question
you see like nation how many thousand
years were still sort of stuck in this
let's say rival risk mode where we again
I was I read Reni Garrard recently and
he's talks about the scapegoat and and
there there's always this need need for
a scapegoat
I mean Gerard is in the air you know
Gerard said right everybody's talking
about Gerard because I think I think
you're like I have an image to hear
people talking more about Ivan Illich
these are thinkers that sort of spoke
before their time and and are now
extremely important it seems to me
totally and Gerard I think is again he's
misunderstood and smuggled into the
cynical nihilistic narrative when in
fact Gerard is a Christian yeah and the
way you end scapegoating is by imitating
Christ you know that Christ taught us to
stop this scapegoating this
Gatewood always returns as the Savior
were the thing that this you know that
actually coheres the community and so
people miss Reid Gerard is saying almost
like an evolutionary biologist that were
stuck in mimetic violence and that we're
stuck in competition all right that's
what they read him as well like we
evolved and the humans are the tragic
creatures that are stuck in the
scapegoated human kill the tragic meat
machines that are stuck in the rival RIS
game when actually he's saying we could
be but Jesus but religion well yeah and
he's saying that there's sort of a
progressive unfolding of the truth going
on
Caressa at the same time as all of all
of this terrible terrible corruption
yeah totally and as a development
obviously yeah and as a developmental
psychologist it seems clear that there
are certain levels of development when
forms of memetic violence and imitation
lock-in but there are post conventional
forms of identity development where are
the idea that the motivation for your
behavior would be entirely mimetic is
actually absurd and so there's not a cap
there if there appears to be a cap on
the Gerardi and development that
everyone is stuck like on Facebook in
mimetic violence and that's why it's
designed that way by the way because the
connection with rutile and Gerard but
but the deeper story is actually no
Gerard himself says there's a way out of
this dynamic of memetic violence which
leads to scapegoating and those types of
the way out even if you weren't a
Christian would still be the Messiah and
the Messiah technically means in Hebrew
they're raising or the changing of
conversation yes and so yeah you're
correct that the way out even if you're
not a Christian is to move into post
conventional forms of more autonomous
and sovereign identity which would allow
you to not imitate violence when you see
it to make yourself subject to it in
order to stop it and so this is the
lesson of Christ and again it's about
staying in the tragedy not avoiding the
tragedy and leave good dynamic is about
avoiding the tragedy whereas the you
know as your Rob's massive collective
denial of some kind yeah right yeah and
so again it's interesting that I think
Gerard is read into as a cynical
narrative when I actually read him as a
kind of a Christian mystic almost like
if you take it seriously enough and see
the way life is getting into myth no I
agree with you I well I think he's if
you read them correctly it's it's it's
good news right kind of good news but
it's but it's still good news right if
getting nailed to the cross is good news
well the ego has to be crucified and you
know perhaps think of it that way or is
that right no that's a good way to think
about when you think about the demands
of consolidating identity
post-convention levels yeah it's uh you
know as Maslow said about the self
transcending that it's the altar on
which you sacrifice your ego not the
means by which you gratify your ego but
the whole term which you sacrificed it
means it's not the thing you think it is
often where you find self transcendence
an actual maturity mm-hmm yeah